Thomas Flöss

Postdoctoral researcher in cosmology

tsfloss@gmail.com

tsfloss

in tsfloss

thomasfloss.com

D 0000-0002-8245-780X



I am a postdoc at the University of Vienna. I work primarily on using late-time cosmological probes, such as the CMB, galaxy surveys, and intensity mapping (e.g. 21-cm) to study the primordial universe, particularly cosmic inflation through primordial non-Gaussianity. In my research, I make use of analytical, numerical and state-of-the-art machine learning (ML) methods. Additionally, I like to think about formal aspects of cosmology such as consistency conditions and the cosmological bootstrap. I have also studied the amplitude double copy, its application to cosmology, and a possible connection with massive gravity. I received my PhD from the University of Groningen in 2024.

Professional Experience

2024 – present

Postdoc in theoretical and computational cosmology, University of Vienna Researcher and teaching assistant ("University Assistant") in the cosmology group led by Univ.-Prof. Oliver Hahn

2020 - 2024

- PhD in Theoretical Cosmology (cum laude), University of Groningen Thesis: A Skewed Perspective on the Universe Advisors: Prof. Diederik Roest, Dr. Daan Meerburg, Prof. Léon Koopmans
 - Determined the feasibility of a lunar-based 21-cm survey for constraining primordial non-Gaussianity using the three- and four-point correlation function
 - Uncovered the impact and importance of including non-Gaussian covariance when constraining primordial non-Gaussianity using the bispectrum
 - Developed and quantified ML-based reconstruction methods for recovering the information content of summary statistics lost due to non-Gaussian covariance
 - Applied state-of-the-art generative ML models to probabilistic CMB-lensing reconstruction
 - · Derived duality-invariant non-linear electrodynamics from massive gravity

During my PhD I co-authored 7 research papers of which 5 as first author.

Education

2016 – 2018

MSc. Theoretical Physics, Utrecht University

Thesis: Inflationary Consistency Conditions and Shift-Symmetric Cosmologies Advisors: Dr. Enrico Pajer and Dr. Garrett Goon. | GPA: 4.0/4.0

2013 - 2016

■ BSc. Physics & Astronomy, Utrecht University

Thesis: Quantum Fluctuations and Magnon-Magnon Interactions in Antiferromagnets Advisors: Prof. Rembert Duine and Dr. Scott Bender. | GPA: 4.0/4.0

Awards & Grants

Sept 2020

Fundamentals of the Universe PhD Scholarship, University of Groningen Research proposal: Sensing in the Dark: exploring the early universe through the Dark Ages.

Research Visits

Sept - Nov 2023

Center for Computational Astrophysics (Flatiron Institute), New York, USA Guest researcher with Franscisco Villaescusa-Navarro and William Coulton

Teaching & Mentoring

2023 Co-supervisor MSc. student Jelte Bottema, University of Groningen

2021 Co-supervisor MSc. student Jorik Melsen, University of Groningen

Teaching Assistant, General Relativity (MSc. course), University of Groningen

2020 Co-supervisor MSc. students Tim de Wild and Tom Westerdijk, University of Groningen

Teaching Assistant, Calculus II (BSc. course), Utrecht University

Organization

2020 – 2023 Cosmology Journal Club, University of Groningen

2020 – 2021 Seminar Series on Cosmological Correlators and Bootstrap, University of Groningen

2015 Physics Symposium "Physical Creativity", Utrecht University

Skills

Languages English (Fluent), Dutch (Native), German (Proficient)

Coding Python, JAX, TensorFlow, julia, PyTorch, C/C++, LaTeX, Mathematica (incl. xAct), GitHub

Public Codes (see GitHub)

PolyBin3D: a GPU accelerated unwindowed power spectrum and bispectrum estimator in Python (together with Oliver Philcox)

BFast: a GPU accelerated FFT bispectrum estimator in JAX (Python)

PyNG: Fisher forecast primordial non-Gaussianity including non-Gaussian covariance

21cmDA: Fisher forecast primordial non-Gaussianity from the Dark Ages' 21-cm signal

Talks & Posters

July 2024 Cosmology in the Adriatic, Split, Croatia (contributed talk)

New Strategies for Extracting Cosmology from Galaxy Surveys, Sexten, Italy (contributed talk)

CMBAS/CCA group meeting, Flatiron Institute

May 2023 Weniger group meeting, GRAPPA, University of Amsterdam

Mar 2023 Netherlands Theoretical Cosmology (THC) meeting

Dec 2022 Hill group meeting, Columbia University

Sep 2022 NOR2022, International Conference, ITF Madrid (contributed talk)

May 2022 Rapteyn Institute Lunch Talk, University of Groningen

Apr 2022 Fundamentals of the Universe Symposium, University of Groningen (invited talk)

State of the Universe Seminar, TIFR, India (invited talk, online)

Feb 2022 Friday Journal Club, KICP, UChicago (invited talk, online)

Talks & Posters (continued)

Sept 2021 Fundamentals of the Universe Symposium, University of Groningen (poster)

Research Publications

- [1] **T. Flöss**, W. R. Coulton, A. J. Duivenvoorden, F. Villaescusa-Navarro, and B. D. Wandelt, "Denoising diffusion delensing: reconstructing the non-Gaussian CMB lensing potential with diffusion models," *Mon. Not. Roy. Astron. Soc.*, vol. 533, no. 1, pp. 423–432, 2024. ODI: 10.1093/mnras/stae1818. arXiv: 2405.05598 [astro-ph.CO].
- [2] O. H. E. Philcox and **T. Flöss**, "PolyBin₃D: A Suite of Optimal and Efficient Power Spectrum and Bispectrum Estimators for Large-Scale Structure," Apr. 2024. arXiv: 2404.07249 [astro-ph.CO].
- [3] **T. Flöss**, D. Roest, and T. Westerdijk, "Non-linear Electrodynamics from Massive Gravity," Aug. 2023, Submitted to JHEP. arXiv: 2308.04349 [hep-th].
- [4] G. Orlando, **T. Flöss**, P. D. Meerburg, and J. Silk, "Local non-Gaussianities from cross-correlations between the CMB and 21-cm," Jul. 2023, Submitted to PRD. arXiv: 2307.15046 [astro-ph.CO].
- [5] **T. Flöss** and P. D. Meerburg, "Improving constraints on primordial non-Gaussianity using neural network based reconstruction," May 2023, Accepted in JCAP. arXiv: 2305.07018 [astro-ph.CO].
- [6] **T. Flöss**, M. Biagetti, and P. D. Meerburg, "Primordial non-Gaussianity and non-Gaussian covariance," *Phys. Rev. D*, vol. 107, no. 2, p. 023 528, 2023. ODI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.107.023528. arXiv: 2206.10458 [astro-ph.CO].
- [7] **T. Flöss**, T. de Wild, P. D. Meerburg, and L. V. E. Koopmans, "The Dark Ages' 21-cm trispectrum," *JCAP*, vol. o6, no. o6, p. o2o, 2022. ODI: 10.1088/1475-7516/2022/06/020. arXiv: 2201.08843 [astro-ph.CO].

References

Prof. Diederik Roest

Full Professor University of Groningen, NL PhD advisor

✓ d.roest@rug.nl

Dr. Franscisco Villaescusa-Navarro

Associate Research Scientist Flatiron Institute, New York, USA Scientific collaborator

Dr. Daan Meerburg

Assistant Professor University of Groningen, NL PhD advisor

p.d.meerburg@rug.nl